Robert Finn Papers MC302
Public Policy Papers
Robert Finn Papers
1970-2014
Public Policy Papers
Finn, Robert
MC302
7.92 linear feet (7 containers)
Robert Finn is a an American diplomat, a lecturer in Turkish Studies and International Relations, and a translator of Turkish fiction and poetry. The Robert Finn Papers consist of writings, drafts, speeches, photographs, and a number of audiovisual materials related to Ambassador Finn's career as a diplomat, translator, and Princeton lecturer.
Content Description
The Robert Finn Papers consist of writings, drafts, speeches, photographs, and a number of audiovisual materials related to Ambassador Finn's career as a diplomat, translator, and Princeton lecturer. The collection documents Finn's Foreign Service career in Pakistan, Turkey, Azerbaijan, Croatia, Tajikistan, and Afghanistan. Additionally there is a significant amout of materials related to Finn's career as a translator of Turkish fiction and poetry, as well as appointment books, speeches and talks, and some commemorative plaques, certificates, and awards.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use, except for five folders in Box 2 (Foreign Service Employee Evaluation Reports and Application for Retirement) which are restricted during the lifetime of the donor due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
Appraisal
Some personal items and duplicate photographs were separated from the collection and returned to the donor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Robert Finn in 2020. The accession number associated with this donation is ML-2020-06.
Finn
Biographical / Historical
Robert Finn is a an American diplomat, a lecturer in Turkish Studies and International Relations, and a translator of Turkish fiction and poetry. Finn studied at St. John's University and New York University before earning a Ph.D. in Near Eastern Studies from Princeton University in 1978. Beginning as a Foreign Service member in 1978, Finn served in Pakistan, Turkey, Azerbaijan, Croatia, Tajikistan, and Afghanistan. He was the first ambassador to Afghanistan in over 20 years when he assumed the office in 2002. He served in Afghanistan until 2004, and retired from the Foreign Service in 2005.
- Foreign Service, 1978-2009; 2 boxes
  - Notepad, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Amb. Finn Art Collection Shipping Inventory, 1996; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - The Afghanistan Connection, proposal by Ambassador Robert Finn, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Ambassadorial documents, circa 1998-2001; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Amb Finn - Photos + CV + Copies of Passport, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - International Muğam Festival Program, circa 2005; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Silk Road Map, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Virgül (Magazine), 2004; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1995-2000; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Afghan Airforce Assessment, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - The Caucasus Region Map and Gazetteer of Populated Places, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - The Ambassadorial Seminar (Notebook), undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Orientation Program for Foreign Service Officers [Group photos], 1978 August 22-1978 September 29; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Representational Voucher - Ambassador Finn, 2002-2003; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1999-2001; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Representational Vouchers, 1999-2001; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1999-2001; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Swearing In Ceremony, 1998; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, circa 1999-2004; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Robert Finn Confirmation Hearing - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1998; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - State Department Purchase Orders, 2003; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - State Department FOIA Documents, 2011; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - To Our Ambassador, circa 2001; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Tajikistan Directory and Business Cards, 1999; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 25th Anniversary of Karadeniz (Black Sea) Technical University, 1981; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1998; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Clippings, 1984-1989; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Clippings, circa 1985-1991; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Foreign Service Photographs and Memorabilia, circa 1993-1998; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Colin Powell Letter of Appreciaton and Clippings, circa 2003-2009; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2006; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Ambassador Finn's Arrival at Post, 2002; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Book: The Modern Ambassador: The Challenge and the Search, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Azerbaijan, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: One World, Turkey, undated; 2 items (Box 2)
  - VHS: Robert Finn, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Turkey Econ Turmoil VOA/WN 3/01, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Taliban VOA/WN 3/01, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Farewell Party hosted in honor of H.E. Mr. Robert Patrick Finn...and his Deputy Mr. Bred Hanson, 2003 July 29; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: PAIYVAND, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Simmons College Warburg Lecture, Afghanistan: The Back Burner Again?, 2004 January 28; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - VHS: Robert's last chat with Pres Aliyev, undated; 1 item (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, circa 1984-1985; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - 9/18/10 Hurra TV, 2010 September 18; 756 MB
    Scope and Contents
  - Azerbaycan, 2007 May 22; 3.31 GB
  - International Forum "Afghanistan 5 Years Later", 2006 October 24; 5.65 GB
  - Kirgizistan, 2007 May 22; 3.82 GB
  - Robert Finn Interview Spring 06, 2006 June 06; 6.29 GB
  - Photographs: Helicopter Flight Over Mountains in Kazakhstan, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Photographs: Dushanbe, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Washington Photos, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Helena Finn and Robert Finn Photos, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 3/03 Charikar Natsios Wheat Sowing, 2002 June 11; 15 MB
  - Amb. Finn Bamyian, 2002 August 05; 25 MB
  - Task Force Kabul Photo Album, 2002 December 7 - 2003 May 4; 590 MB
  - Duralaman Palace, 2003 January 30; 13 MB
  - Welcome to Shahi Qala School Opening Ceremony, 2003 May 07; 292 MB
  - 2003 4th of July Kabul Awards Ceremony, 2003 July 04; 34 MB
  - Khorog Badakshan, 2003 September 30; 632 MB
  - Afghanistan 2, Almaty, Lake Issikul, Pamirs, Seven Lakes, etc., 2003 October 17; 485 MB
  - Magical Mystery Tour 1, 2003 October 17; 562 MB
  - Magical Mystery Tour 2, 2003 October 17; 523 MB
  - Afghanistan (Rishma's Photos), 2003 October 17; 683 MB
  - Ambassador Finn CAREs about Tajikistan, 2007 July 08; 35 MB
  - Foreign Service Employee Evaluation Reports, 1991-2005; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted during lifetime of donor due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
  - Robert Finn Application for Retirement, 2005; 1 folder (Box 2)
- Academic and Translation Materials, circa 1974-2011; 3 boxes
  - Seventeen Elegies for Sait Salim Halman, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Orpheus by Nazli Eray, translation by Robert Finn, circa 2005; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - 105 [Modern Turkish Poetry], 2009; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Syllabi, circa 2004; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - The United States and Croatia: A Documentary History 1992-1997, circa 1997; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and notes, circa 2008; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, circa 2005; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Princeton University Job Offers, 2005-2011; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Translation Contracts, 2010; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 2006-2012; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - German Newspaper clipping sent to Helena Finn, 2009 April 1; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Some Female Characters in Turkish Fiction, article and correspondence, 1999; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Teaching, Translation, Correspondence, circa 1994-2011; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Hatiralar, 2008 March 26; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research and Translation Materials, circa 2007-2011; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - WWS Student Evaluations of the Undergraduate Policy Seminars, 2010; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research, Teaching, and Translation Materials, circa 2004-2005; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Turkish Reading Course, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research and Writings, circa 2004; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 2006-2007; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research, Teaching, and Clippings, circa 2003-2004; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Personal and School Papers, circa 1972-1976; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research Paper, circa 1970s; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - School Papers, circa 1974; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - School Papers, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - The Armchair by Aziz Nesin, translated by Robert Finn, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - School Papers, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Paper on Turkish Literature, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Research and Translation Materials, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Research Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Mansion for Rent by Yakup Kadri Karaosmanoglu, translated by Robert Finn, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - In the White Garden by Tomris Uyar, translated by Robert Finn, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Tranlsation Materials, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The Early Turkish Novel by Robert Finn (bound thesis), 1978; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Turkish Manuscript, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Mansion for Rent by Yakup Kadri Karaosmanoglu, translated by Robert Finn [manuscript with notes], undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Research Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Galeri Baraz Poster: Zeki Findikoglu, 1987-1988; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Tranlsation Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - You're Hurt by Erdal Oz, translated by Robert Finn, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Research Materials: "The Poet Disillusioned: Halit Ziya Usakligil's Mai ve Siyah", circa 1984; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Tranlsation Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence re: translation of Orhan Pamuk, 1987; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Transalation of Turgut Uyar, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Research and Transalation Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Tranlsation Materials (various authors), circa 1987; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - A Spring Story by Sait Faik Abasiyanik, circa 1990; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Translations (various authors), undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Research and Transalation Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Translation of Beyaz Kale by Orhan Pamuk, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Tranlsation Materials, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
- Speeches, circa 1986-2009; 1 box
  - Speeches, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Afghanistan's Clouded Future - Speech at Liechtenstein Institute on Self Determination, Princeton University, 2010 March 31; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Visions and Revisions: Charting A Common Future for the US and Arab World, 2009 April 24-2009 April 27; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speeches, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Helena Finn - Hazorea 219 (Speech), undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Articles, Speeches, Notes, circa 2003; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Speeches, circa 1998-2009; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - 3/30, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, 2010 May 14; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Ataturk's World View, 2010 December 7; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speech, Women in Turkish Fiction, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Speeches, etc., circa 1986-1992; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Overview of US Foreign Policy Challenges - Hearts and Minds, 2009-02-06T00:00:00+00:00; 1 folder (Box 4)
- Appointment Books, 1986-2014; 20 items (Box 5)
- Memorabilia, Certificates, and Awards, 1982-2003; 1 box
  - Flag Certificate, American Embassy, Kabul, 2002 May-2003 August; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Letters and Certificates of commendation, 2002-2003; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Certificate of Commendation, U.S. Marine Corps, 2003 April 27; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Group photo and certificate of appreciation: Pipelines and Fault Lines, the Future of Energy Security in Asia, 2003 October 21-23; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - State Department Retirement Plaque Letter, 2006 July 26; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Award plaques, circa 2005; 5 items (Box 6)
  - Oversized Patch: September 11, 2001 World Trade Center Fallen Heroes, undated; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Japanese Art print, undated; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Commendation Certificate from director of CIA, 1992; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Certificate of Appointment as Career Member of the Senior Foreign Service, 1997 November 25; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Certificate of Appointment as Foreign Service Officer, Consular Officer, and a Secretary of the Diplomatice Service, 1982 June 17; 1 folder (Box 7)